<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the Company of Grocers stated and their condition in their present circumstances truly represented : together with a short accompt of their original, how eminent they have been in the city, and also of some of their antient priviledges and usages designed for information and satisfaction of the members and vindication of the company.</title>
            <author>Ravenhill, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25601</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09025721</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09025721</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42278</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58106)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42278)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1292:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the Company of Grocers stated and their condition in their present circumstances truly represented : together with a short accompt of their original, how eminent they have been in the city, and also of some of their antient priviledges and usages designed for information and satisfaction of the members and vindication of the company.</title>
                  <author>Ravenhill, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 9 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Company of Grocers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: W. Ravenhill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grocers' Company (London, England)</term>
               <term>Guilds --  Great Britain --  History.</term>
               <term>Grocers --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42278:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE Of the COMPANY of GROCERS STATED.</p>
            <p>And their Condition in their Preſent Circumſtances Truly Repreſented.</p>
            <p>Together with a ſhort Accompt of their ORIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAL; How Eminent they have been in this CITY, And alſo of ſome of their Antient PRIVILEDGES and USAGES.</p>
            <p>Deſigned for INFORMATION and SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISFACTION of the MEMBERS, And VINDICATION of the COMPANY,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Company of <hi>Grocers,</hi> An. Dom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42278:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42278:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right HONOURABLE, Right WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFUL, and the reſt of the Worthy MEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERS of the SOCIETY of the MISTERY of GROCERY, <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>William Ravenhill</hi> their Clerk, humbly offers and prayes their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and peruſal of theſe following Papers; As a Teſtimony of his Hearty Deſires, and Sincere Endeavours to Vindicate the Reputation, and improve the Intereſt of this Society.</head>
            <p>AS ſoon as by the good Providence of God I obtained the favour, and had the Happineſs to be Choſen your Clerk, I reſolved with my utmoſt Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to purſue and perform my Duty in this place, and thereby grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully anſwer the expectation of my Friends, who promoted by Election; and alſo lay hold of ſo fair an opportunity to ingratiate my ſelf into the Favour and Eſteem of Good Men: Being Convinced, that if I ſhould neglect my Duty, it would render my Follies and Ingratitude more conſpicuous to the World. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I might in doing the one avoid the other, I endeavoured in the firſt place to inform my ſelf of the true State and Condition of the Company; upon Inqueſt whereof, I found it plain and manifeſt, That for want of Knowledge of the Truth ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of, not only many Worthy Benefactors with-held their Aſſiſtance towards diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Debts and Charities, But alſo many Reproaches and Reflections were caſt upon this Society; Both from Strangers (with whom they have been no way concerned) And alſo their Creditors who rendred them obnoxions in Courts of Law and Equity, And before the Commiſſioners for Charitable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes; As if they had been a Company that poſſeſſed a great Revenue, ſufficient to pay all their Debts, Yet were ſo averſe from doing that, that they waſted and Conſumed their Eſtate in Feaſting themſelves, refuſing to pay, unleſs they were Compell'd by Chargeable Suits; which not only aggravated their Creditors, but alienated the Affections of many good Perſons, As well Members as others; and cauſed many Chargeable Suits and Vexatious Proſecutions against them, Notwithſtanding the Care and Endeavours of ſome Worthy and Good Members, who uſed all poſſible means to avoid the ſame. For I cannot deny, but that ſo long as I was ignorant of the Truth of their Caſe (though I was an unworthy Member) Yet I was perſwaded to believe many things reported of the <hi>Grocers,</hi> which I now find to be far otherwiſe. Therefore I made it my great deſign to acquaint my ſelf with all their Affairs, and past tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I might be able to make a true repreſentation of the Companies Condition as to all Subſtantial matters, Both what it was before they Contracted their Debts,
<pb facs="tcp:42278:3"/>and how they became indebted, what they have already done towards it, and what means and methods they may beſt uſe, and proſecute to diſcharge themſelves, to the end thoſe great Reproaches and Prejudices (which through miſ-apprehenſions and falſe Reports have been cast on this Company) may be removed. And every true hearted Member that bears a Chriſtian reſpect to the Pious Memory of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors (who were Worthy Benefactors) and would in diſcharge of his Duty Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelf, after their Example, to Poſterity, may willingly and chearfully lay to his helping hand. And as a further Teſtimony of my hearty deſires to ſerve the Members, having ſo briefly ſtated the Companies Caſe, I ſhall endeavour to give you a ſhort Account of the Antiquity and firſt Creation and Continuance of the <hi>Grocers,</hi> as far and clear as I can make Conjecture or have received any probable Account. As to that part of my Duty which relates to the Regulating and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesting the Companies Books into an orderly Method, as alſo their Evidences to clear their Titles to their ſeveral Rents, Lands and Houſes, and the ſeveral Schools under their Government; And alſo the ſeveral Eccleſiaſtical Livings in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this Society, with the names of their Founders, and how they became Veſted in their Right; And alſo other Priviledges peculiar to this Society, I have already made ſuch Progreſs and doubt not ſpeedily to Compleat it, ſo as it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear obvious and plain to be understood by every individual Member, Of which it will not be proper here to give an Account, But I refer to the Books and Records themſelves, more fit to be inſpected at this Hall by ſuch as have right to know them, than to be expoſed to view of others whom it no way Concerns.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="case">
            <pb facs="tcp:42278:3"/>
            <head>The COMPANIES CASE briefly stated.</head>
            <p>MOſt part of the ſaid Companies Revenues is charged with yearly Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſeveral Pariſhes, Places, and Uſes amounting to near the yearly profits they receive. Moſt part whereof conſiſted of Houſes in <hi>London,</hi> which were all conſumed by the late dreadful Fire, when they expected to have advanced great Sums of Money by way of Fine, on Renewing of Leaſes towards payment of their Debts.</p>
            <p>They had alſo heretofore many and great Sums of Money paid into their hands as a Fund for the Uſes following, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To pay yearly Sums in Coals, Faggots, and Money to ſeveral Pariſhes and Wards about <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
            <p>To ſeveral Priſons for Redemption and Releaſe of Priſoners.</p>
            <p>To the poor Members of the Company.</p>
            <p>To be lent to Young Men that had ſerved their Times to Members of this Company on Security, with little or no Intereſt, to ſet up, and to be returned again.</p>
            <p>To buy Impropriations for maintenance of Miniſters where Livings are ſmall, And To maintain ſeveral Schools and Alms-Houſes.</p>
            <p>They complyed punctually with all their Truſts, continuing in very great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Reputation, until the ſad effects of War and Fire rendred them uncapable to diſcharge their yearly Charities where they have no fund left. And,</p>
            <p>The remaining part of their great Debts which they Contracted, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 1640. To Accommodate the late King in his Exigencies, on Security of ſome of his Peers.</cell>
                     <cell>4500 <hi>l.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 1642. To Subdue the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Relieve the Proteſtants there.</cell>
                     <cell>9000 <hi>l.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 1643. To lend the City, for which, they had their Seal.</cell>
                     <cell>4500</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>All which they took up on their Common Seal, nor were Singular therein, but neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated thereto in complyance with all other Companies, and indeed with the whole City.</p>
            <p>Upon their taking up this Money, they made a By-Law to levy the ſame on themſelves, if their Stock fell ſhort; and ſo they continued payment of their Intereſt. And as one Creditor called for his Money in, they took up of others, and paid them off; Depending upon getting in their ſaid Principal. All which failed them, till at laſt their ſole hope was of advancing Money by Renewing of Leaſes. Many whereof were nigh expired. But the Fire in 1666 Conſumed their whole Revenue in <hi>London;</hi> They having already paid for Intereſt of Money between 1640, and 1666. — 30000 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As their Debts exceeded any other Companies, ſo their loſs herein was exceeding great, ſo that now they were uncapable any longer to pay Debts or Charities.</p>
            <p>They applyed themſelves to the Parliament then ſitting on their By-Law, But were rejected as binding to no more then were parties to it, moſt of whom were dead.</p>
            <p>They had then no means to raiſe Money, but by letting their Ground to Builders for Fines on Long Leaſes; great part whereof they were compelled to, by decree of the Judges at <hi>Cliffords</hi>-Inn.</p>
            <p>And by voluntary Subſcriptions, both which were ſet on foot ſoon after the Fire: And to Encourage Subſcriptions, Sir <hi>John Cutler</hi> Erected the firſt Building in the Garden.</p>
            <p>They raiſed Conſiderable Sums, and propounded to pay their Creditors their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part thereof down, and the reſt at two payments.</p>
            <p>And after many meetings moſt of their Creditors inclined to accept ſuch propoſal, finding how it muſt be advanced. But ſome of their Members being backward, and ſome Creditors ill adviſed, Sued the Company, and Seized their Hall in Ruines which put a ſtop to all; though thoſe Creditors themſelves repent this: Afterwards looſing their Charges, and glad to comply on lower terms than at firſt offered.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the Company raiſe Money what they could of kind Members themſelves, and take up the reſidue on their Aſſignment of the Sequeſtration and Conveyance of all their Eſtate to pay off the Creditors that Sequeſtred. And ſome other remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proportions to Creditors who had not yet received any. And to ſupply what was wanting, they let their Land in <hi>Ireland</hi> on Fine, ſinking the Rent to 10 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi> But the Hall continuing in Ruines, the Company was thereby rendred Reproachful.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The Apprentices bound at other Halls, and turned over.</item>
               <item>The Freemen take their Freedoms of other Companies.</item>
               <item>And all Benefactors decline as deſpairing of any good to Poſterity.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42278:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>So that the Members every year dying and failing, and many removing into the Country, and none to ſucceed in their places.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs follow that the Company in few years muſt diſſolve for want of a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Members:</p>
            <p>Which would moſt reproachfully have rendred the Members then living, who were numerous and equal, if not more eminent than any other Company. Not only moſt ungrateful to their Predeceſſors who have been ſo liberal Benefactors, and have left ſuch Grounds (though the Buildings were ſo conſumed by the Fire) yet now built on, gives a great hope to poſterity) but alſo obnoxious to poſterity.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration whereof alone, moved the Right Honourable Sir <hi>John Moore,</hi> the preſent Lord Mayor, to repair the Hall, and alſo upon further Conſideration, the reſt of the Aldermen and other kind Members to enlarge it with Commodious Buildings for the Seat of a chief Magiſtrate. That it might not only encourage the Freemen, Apprentices and Benefactors to preſerve the Company a Nurſery of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Seminary of good Citizens. But alſo anſwer the Charge of the Building, in proving the yearly Revenue of the Company: And is indeed (if rightly conſidered) in the Companies preſent Circumſtances, of greater advantage to the Company, than any one thing that hath been done for them. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It hath already incouraged the Apprentices and Freemen, ſo that whereas there uſed to be bound 1, 2, or 3 Apprentices in a Moneth, and 1, or 2 made free before, and thoſe but poor Artificers; they are generally now encreaſed to a far greater Number, As well of Free-men, as Apprentices, and many of them of good Quality.</p>
            <p n="2">II. It hath given great ſatisfaction to ſeveral Eminent Members, who have declared themſelves very inclinable to Contribute largely towards diſcharge of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Debts and Charities, if they ſee but any Encouragement from the reſt of the Members.</p>
            <p n="3">III. This Building, though it amounts to much more then what it was at firſt deſigned, Yet a great part thereof hath been freely laid down on purpoſe for this work. And whatever is further laid down towards it, (which its hoped the whole will be raiſed by kind Members to anſwer theſe goods ends) would never have been ſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but for this very purpoſe.</p>
            <p>So that in all probability, the Hall (if the Company pleaſe) may be every year diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of for 200 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> at the leaſt (which being no way clogged (as the reſt is, with Charities) Is more than two-fold, better than all the reſt of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Revenue they now receive beſides.</p>
            <p>And that the Building and Beautifying the Hall may not be a bait to Creditors again to ſeize it. So again to diſcourage the Members.</p>
            <p>The Hall, and all the Companies Revenue is by advice of Counſel conveyed to Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offees in truſt.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Subject to ſecure the Money ſo taken up to diſcharge the Sequeſtrations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when thoſe and what Moneys they ſhould be ſo neceſſitated to take up to compleat the Buildings ſhall be diſcharged.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Then to ſecure the yearly Charities wherewith the Company is Chargeable. By many Benefactors who ſo heretofore left Moneys in their Hands, as a Fund to ſecure the ſame. No part whereof now remains, As being a truſt they are liable in the firſt place, As a Duty incumbent on them both to avoid a Curſe, and in order to obtain a Bleſſing from God upon their endeavours: As alſo to avoid proſecution of the Commiſſioners upon the Statute for Charitable Uſes, who have yearly put the Company to vaſt expences already upon that Accompt.</p>
            <p>And theſe things having been made known to the Creditors, The Company have been free from Suits and Proſecutions which they never before were ſince their troubles firſt began.</p>
            <p>Which inclines their Creditors to comply upon any reaſonable terms, and as ſome have already accepted, and are diſcharged: So many others are importunate to do the like: And now ſo fair an opportunity being offered to deliver the Company, and to give Encouragement to Benefactors. It is hoped there is no Member but will chearfully embrace it, whereby they ſhall not only draw others on by their Example to preſerve this Society, ſtill a Nurſery of Charity, and Seminary of good Citizens; But alſo encourage Benefactors for the future; ſome in their Lives, and others at their death liberally to extend their kindneſs towards this Company, And without all doubt, ſuch works as theſe are acceptable to God in times of greateſt trouble and danger.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42278:4"/>
            <head>A ſhort Accompt of the Original of the <hi>GROCERS,</hi> and their first Incorporation; And their Condition in their preſent Circumstances truly Repreſented.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Grocers</hi> (inquit <hi>Minſhew</hi>) ab initio ut ex legibus nostris probat, nihil minutim ſed omnia al <hi>groſſo, by the great.</hi> Magnis ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ponderibus divendere ſoliti ſunt. In libro statutorum noſtrorum ſignificat Mercatores, Qui aliquod mercium genus totum coemunt. <hi>Skin. Etymologicon linguae Anglicanae.</hi>
               </note>THE word <hi>Grocers</hi> was a Term at firſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Merchants of this Society in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Inferiour Retailers, For that they uſually ſold in groſs Quantities by great Weights. And in ſome of our old Books the Word ſignifies Merchants that in their Merchandizing dealt for the whole of any kind: But in after times the word <hi>Grocery</hi> became ſo extenſive that it can now hardly be reſtrained to the certain kinds of Merchandizes, they have formerly dealt in. For they have been the moſt Univerſal Merchants that traded abroad, And what they brought home many Artiſts of this Society found out ways afterwards to Change and alter the Species by mixture, Confections, and Compoſitions of ſimple ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients; By which means many and various ways of dealing and trading paſſed under the Denomination of <hi>Groceries.</hi> And indeed this City and Nation do in a great meaſure owe the Improvement of Navigation to theſe Merchants, originally exerciſing this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, as trading into all foreign parts, From whence we have received either Spices, Druggs, Fruits, Gums, or other rich Aromatick Commodities, It is well known this Company hath bred the moſt Eminent Merchants in this City, and this Society hath been ſo prolifick that many other Societies have been branched out from hence, as will be owned by the moſt worthy of them; The Merchants Trading to the <hi>Levant</hi> Seas, and other Societies have originally been the off-ſpring of this Society, as appears by antient Records of Indentures of Apprentices to Members of this Company; And it is not inconſiſtent, and may be within compaſs of Belief, That there was amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> a Society agreeable to this of the <hi>Grocers,</hi> who were alſo Merchants trading in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe Seas, as may be Collected from <hi>Perſius</hi> a Poet who wrote in <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> deſcribing the various Inclinations of men in their Courſe of Life, He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances them in theſe words, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Mercibus hic <hi>Italis</hi> mutat ſub ſole recenti</l>
               <l>Rugoſum piper, &amp; pallentis Grana Cymini:</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sat. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>With Merchandizing this with Care doth run</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Eaſt under the riſing Sun</l>
               <l>To fetch rough Pepper and pale Cummin Seeds</l>
               <l>For <hi>Roman</hi> Wares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Where Pepper, being the moſt Royal and preſervative Spice, is only mentioned by way of Eminency for all the reſt; And ſo we may well conclude that this was the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the Society of the <hi>Grocers</hi> (whoſe Original firſt here exerciſed, may modeſtly be ſuppoſed to ſpring from the <hi>Romans</hi>) were long before they were Incorporated, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>Pepperers,</hi> although they traded before in all other the former Merchandizes, as well as that. It is impoſſible to give any other Accompt of the Original of this Society, here in this City ſo long at firſt exerciſed under the Denomination of <hi>Pepperers;</hi> For that, the City of <hi>London</hi> it ſelf, at firſt under the <hi>Britains,</hi> and ſucceſſively after under the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Saxons,</hi> and at laſt was over-run by the <hi>Danes.</hi> No Hiſtory now remains to give a certain Account of the firſt Methods of Government therein, further than what may be Collected from ſome late Writers of our own now extant, who have tranſmitted to us, what they could then diſcover by their Enquiry and Search in Antiquity, whereby we may plainly underſtand that the firſt Model of Government ſetled in this City, was from the Example of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, as Mr. <hi>Stow</hi> inſtances in the very words of an ancient writer, who wrote in the Reign of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> (viz.) <hi>This City</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>even as</hi> Rome) <hi>is divided into Wards, it hath yearly Sheriffs inſtead of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, it hath the Dignity of Senators, it hath under Officers, and according to the Qualities of Laws it hath ſeveral Courts and general Aſſemblies upon appointed dayes.</hi> And their Chief
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42278:5"/>Miniſters of Law were ſtiled Portgraves (which is the ſame as Sheriff) long before they went under the name of Sheriff. Soon after the City obtained their Chief Magiſtrate to be under the Denomination of Mayor, which was about the firſt year of King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt. And the firſt man we find advanced to that Dignity was <hi>Henry Fitz-Alwin,</hi> who continued therein 24 years ſucceſſively; And afterwards for many years the Cheif Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate was ſometimes ſtiled <hi>Cuſtos,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Mayor.</hi> And ſoon after (to wit) in the 17th. year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, it appears <hi>Andrew Bokerell</hi> a Pepperer was Choſen Mayor, and ſo eminent were the Pepperers in this Infancy of the Mayoralty that before the 36 year of that Kings Reign a Pepperer had the Chair 9 ſeveral years, and very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently afterwards we find the Pepperers advanced to that Dignity. Which Society of the Pepperers encreaſing and ſpreading ſo Univerſal in Merchandizing, that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears they were diſtinguiſhed as well by the name of <hi>Grocers</hi> (being a more compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive name) as Pepperers. Inſomuch that before they were incorporated by the Name of <hi>Grocers</hi> (to wit) in the 3d. year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d, <hi>Anno</hi> 1329. <hi>John Grantham</hi> was Choſen and held Mayor by the Title of <hi>Grocer.</hi> And the firſt Charter I find of the Corporation of the <hi>Grocers</hi> was granted by King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. in the 20th year of his Reign, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1345, which appears to be long before the <hi>Mercers</hi> were Incorporated, though they are now the only Company have precedency of the <hi>Grocers;</hi> Yet for the Reaſons above-mentioned, it may be very well preſumed, That as the <hi>Grocers</hi> were long before them the moſt Eminent Society, ſo in after times renewing their Charter by a more Comprehenſive Term they might Poſt-pone themſelves.</p>
            <p>But though they thus march as a forlorn Regiment in the Front, (might the hopes and endeavours of many good Members prevail to have the Spirit of our Anceſtors revived in the preſent Generation) This could no more Eclipſe the <hi>Grocers</hi> who have all the Noble Army of the reſt of the Corporations following them, than the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Star uſhering in Day before it, can eclipſe the Glory of the Riſing Sun.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the Charter of this Company was ſeveral times renewed, as alſo it was in the 7th year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. and they then made a Body Politique, by the name of <hi>Cuſtodes &amp; Communitas Myſterij</hi> Grocerij Londini; <hi>The Wardens and Commonalty of the Myſtery of the</hi> Grocery <hi>of</hi> London. And in the beginning of that Kings Reign they purchaſed the ground where the <hi>Grocers</hi> Hall now ſtands, with the ground belonging to it, of <hi>Walter</hi> Lord <hi>Fitz-water,</hi> bounding the ſame between the <hi>Old-Jury</hi> and <hi>VValbrook.</hi> And ſo Conſiderable in the City were the <hi>Grocers</hi> long before that time, that they were the only men intruſted with the management of the King's Beam, peculiar to them, as principally uſing the ſame; and had the naming of the Weighmaſter, and the nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, placing, removing and governing of the four Porters, all to be Elected out of their own Company, a priviledge allowed them as their undoubted and inſeperate right, as antient as that Office it ſelf uſed in the City, and now at this day upon Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement and Improvement thereof may become of much more advantage to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Company.</p>
            <p>Alſo amongſt other Priviledges and antient Uſages of this Company, I find Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded even as high as <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th's daies, this Company had Power of inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Correction of Abuſes and Irregularities of all Perſons (though free of this or any other Company) in the City or Suburbs, any way uſing or exerciſing any kind of <hi>Grocery;</hi> and alſo to aſſay the Weights they bought or ſold by: And to take notice of all their Defaults, and return them to be Fined at the Diſcretion of this Fellowſhip, and to take 4 d, of every perſon for their Labour therein, as well of ſuch as were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, as ſuch as were not. Which Uſage was alwaies continued, and in the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter renewed to this Company in the 15th. year of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt; this Priviledge is Confirmed and expreſſed to extend three miles from the City as well within Liberties as without, and hath only been omitted for ſome years paſt when the Company began to be firſt interrupted in their Affairs.</p>
            <p>But to return to the purchaſe of the Hall in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. After which the Company flouriſhed with many Eminent and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Members, who became very liberal Benefactors, and had ſo great a ſhare all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in the Senators of this famous City, that they never wanted an Alderman of their Members yearly to ſucceed Maſter Warden of this Company; and ſo faithfully did they acquit themſelves of thoſe Charities they wete intruſted withal, that it gave them the greateſt Reputation of any Company in <hi>London;</hi> Inſomuch that many well diſpoſed Perſons did Covet to make this Corporation as it were the <hi>Corban</hi> of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42278:5"/>their Charities, which in proceſs of time became their Snare, as in this Diſcourſe will immediately appear, wherein I ſhall endeavour by giving a true Account of the Nature of thoſe Charities, to remove the reproach that hath been caſt on this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany as if they had miſ-employed them; And make it plainly appear that the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Grocers</hi> have in the Judgment of every impartial man (who ſhall well weigh their Circumſtances from the firſt to the laſt acquitted themſelves in all the Truſt and Affairs of this Company as becomes Worthy Citizens, and beyond what the worſt of their Detractors might have juſtly expected from them. Eſpecially conſidering how ſmall a part of their yearly Revenue Remains to the Company, when the Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Payments Iſſuing thereout, purſuant to the Diſpoſition of the Donors are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted.</p>
            <p>FOR moſt part of all the Land and Houſes given to the <hi>Grocers</hi> Company were by the Donors charged with yearly Charities iſſuing thereout to certain uſes, well nigh amounting to as much as the rent reſerved upon long Leaſes in being, before they Contracted any of their Debts, as is hereafter mentioned; All or moſt part of which lay in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the ſame Leaſes many of them were nigh expiring about the time of the late dreadful Fire.</p>
            <p>Thoſe other Charities which were Summs of Money, given by ſeveral Benefactors into this Company (there to remain as a fund) were charged with yearly payments iſſuing thereout to certain Pariſhes, Places, and Uſes by the Donors, well nigh as much as the full Intereſt thereof amounted to, or very ſmall advantage to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany over and above the ſame, ſo that the Company were neceſſitated to diſpoſe of thoſe Summs of Money at Intereſt on the beſt Securities they could get, to enable them to make good thoſe yearly Charities. Many of which Securities might in all probability become very backwards in payment, and ſometimes quite Deſperate, ſo that the Company having daily Money preſſed upon them, were inforced to accept the ſame at Intereſt, and thereout continued Conſtant payment of thoſe yearly Summs. And alſo to accommodate Young Men of their Members with Money on Security, to ſet up purſuant to the Wills, of ſeveral Donors of that kind (whereof they had not a few Benefactors) ſo that in time by occaſion of many Loſſes and Caſualties of this Nature, it cannot be imagined but the Company muſt ſuſtain much damage, notwithſtanding all their Care and Endeavours, though they were not in the leaſt ſenſible thereof till they had long after under greater preſſure tried their Securities, Their Credit being very high and in great Reputation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But their Great Debts they Contracted as followeth, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ABout the year 1640 his late Majeſty, King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, having Occaſion for Money in his Exigencies, and making his Condition and Deſires known to this Company, as well as others, they did take up Money upon their Common Seal, and to ſupply him did on Security of ſome of his Peers, accommodate his ſaid Majeſty with 4500 <hi>l.</hi> which (the unhappy War Succeeding) is yet unpaid.</p>
               <p>Afterwards about the year 1642, this Company in Complyance with other Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, and indeed with the whole City, were again required to raiſe 9000 <hi>l.</hi> for the defence of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and releif of the Proteſtants there, which they likewiſe took up upon Security of their Common Seal which was never repaid.</p>
               <p>And afterwards in the year 1643, in Compliance with other Companies, they were induced to lend the City of <hi>London,</hi> 4500 <hi>l.</hi> which they in like manner advanced, and had the Common Seal of the City for Security thereof, ſome ſmall part whereof they afterwards received, the reſidue is yet unpaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe great Loans</hi> were the only Means that brought this Company at laſt into ſuch extremity; Yet did they appear to be ſo juſt in their intentions amongſt themſelves, that having ſo taken theſe great Summs of Money upon their Common Seal of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Perſons at Intereſt, they made a By-Law in their Court of Aſſiſtants to levy the ſame by Aſſeſſement upon themſelves and their Members in caſe their Stock and Eſtate fell ſhort to pay it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42278:6"/>And afterwards from year to year as their Creditors call'd for their Principal, (conſtantly paying the Intereſt as it became due) they took up other Moneys (which was daily offered to the Company) and paid them off.</p>
               <p>About the year 1661, The Company having ſuſtained many loſſes, and their Debts naturally every year encreaſing (they receiving no Intereſt of any to whom they themſelves had ſo lent, and deſpairing of the Principal, and upon Audit of the Wardens Accounts, finding ſuch Prodigious Sums every year ſwallowed up in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of Intereſt) ſeveral of the Members taking the Companies. Condition into Conſideration, moved the Court of Aſſiſtants, and a Committee was appointed to inſpect the ſame, And to conſider of ſome way how to obviate the further encreaſe of the Companies Debts, by diſcharging them Gradually. But (other matters inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening) no progreſs was made therein till afterwards, about the Moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1663, upon the like occaſion they were reminded thereof, and the Committee revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the further Conſideration reſumed; but having ſpent ſome time in conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which way to advance Money, The fair Proſpect they had of advancing Money within a few years by renewing Leaſes of their Eſtates in <hi>London</hi> to diſcharge the greateſt part of their Debts: And having Moneys daily preſſed on them to ſupply their occaſions on Security of their Common Seal, they were not haſty to propoſe the renewing of their Leaſes, Many of them judging it for the Companies advantage to defer that for ſome time longer, And to endeavour to get in their own Debts. In which Circumſtances they continued, till ſoon after, before they had renewed any Leaſes, It pleaſed God the late dreadful Fire happened, whereby not only their Hall, but their whole Revenue in <hi>London</hi> (ſo highly improveable upon expiring Leaſes) was conſumed; And the ſeveral Members then at the Helm, who moſt of them great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffered in their own private Capacities, were ſeperated, and ſo taken up with Care of diſpoſing of themſelves and Families, that very few could attend the Affairs of the Company. And ſo that dreadful Calamity rendred this Company (which ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained ſo great damage therein) utterly uncapable to comply with payment of their Debts an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Charities, which plainly appears by the Wardens Books to have been all along before that time punctually paid and diſcharged as they grew due and were from time to time call'd for and demanded.</p>
               <p>But as ſoon after the Fire as the Members could have freedom from their own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting Affairs, they took the Companies deplorable Condition into their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, And found they had no refuge now left but to propound their ground to Builders for long Leaſes, and advance what Monies they could by way of Fines. And (that they might leave nothing unattempted) their Stock and Eſtate by theſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences falling ſhort to pay thoſe great Debts ſo contracted) they applyed themſelves (on their ſaid By-Law) to the Parliament then ſitting, ſtating their Caſe how great Debts they owed, and how they became ſo indebted, to advance thoſe great ſums which they could never hope to receive, and that although they had receiv'd no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, yet they had before that time paid for Intereſt of the moneys (they had ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up) nigh 30000 <hi>l.</hi> And therefore pray'd an Act of Parliament to put their ſaid By-Law in Execution by Aſſeſſement on their Members. But that was rejected as Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable, that it ſhould bind any more than thoſe who were Parties to the making of it, who were then moſt of them dead. Whereupon as the only means they had then left, they endeavoured to raiſe money by letting their Ground; and what ſhould fall ſhort therein, they propounded to make up among themſelves by a Voluntary Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of their Members; for whoſe Encouragement Sir <hi>John Cutler,</hi> at his own proper Charges, Erected the ſtately Fabrick out of its Aſhes which is now their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and Entertaining Room over it in the Garden, hoping thereby to incite other Members to follow; ſhewing himſelf Zealous beyond all expreſſion to raiſe and reſtore this Company out of its Ruines and Calamity.</p>
               <p>To whoſe Memory the Company (as ſoon as they had afterwards Re-built and Enlarged their Hall) in purſuance of ſeveral Orders of the Court of Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, cauſed his Lively Statue in Effigy in white Marble to be erected on the right hand at the Upper end of the Parlour. And that the ſame may ſurvive the Caſual Accidents of Fire, and Canker of Envy (as the Poet in a higher ſtrain intimated,) <hi>Marmora Maeonii Vincunt Monumenta libelli.</hi> The Memory of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Book ſhould ſurvive his Marble ſtatue in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate-houſe. So my Deſire is hereby to Record ſo Worthy a Benefactor, to the End his Name may be freſh and flouriſhing amongſt the Generations to come, who ſhall in after Ages ſucceed happy Members of this Society.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42278:6"/>And in order to Carry on ſo good a Work, a general Summons was ordered of the Members, and a Committee appointed, and ſeveral meetings had amongſt themſelves to obtain Subſcriptions (wherein a good progreſs was made) and their ground pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to Builders for what Fines they could get under the old rents, (which they could not much leſſen in regard of their Charities iſſuing thereout, wherewith their Donors charged them) in order to advance Money; which accordingly was done, and ſeveral Meetings had with their Creditors. To whom they Propounded to pay their Principal Money, part down, and the reſidue by two Payments, at 5 and 10 years, to be ſecured by their Common Seal. Moſt of their Creditors complying with this fair propoſal, conſidering that the money ſo to be raiſed, muſt be advanced even great part of it by a free Contribution, and Voluntary Gift of the Members, who many of them Liberally contributed; And great Summes were raiſed and paid. But whilſt ſome of the Members were purſuing this good Deſign, and the Company in a hopeful way of wholly diſcharging themſelves, the unkindneſs of ſome and backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of other Members, who ſhould have followed ſo good Examples, gave ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption as occaſioned ſome of their Creditors (inſtigated by inconſiderate and ſelf-ſeeking Agents) unadviſedly to ſue the Company, and the very Ruines of their Hall to be ſequeſtered and ſeized, Although thoſe Creditors, afterwards repented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereof, as ſenſible they had not only put themſelves to great Charge (which they could never be re-imburſed) but had thereby injured the reſt of the Creditors in diſcouraging ſo good a deſign, and obſtructing the gifts of many Worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, of whom ſeveral afterwards died, before their help could be again ſeaſonably ſought for; which wholly Eclipſed the Reputation of the Company, rendering them for the preſent uncapable of further paying; till ſome time after ſeveral Worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers Continuing their endeavours (to carry on ſo good a Work begun) procured Money to be raiſed to pay off part, and more to be lent to diſcharge the reſt of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations, by perſons, to whom their Creditors aſſigned the ſame by direction of the Company; And by letting their Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſinking the Rent to 10 <hi>l. per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and thereby, as alſo by Caſual Profits, Benevolences and Gifts of their Members, paid of a good part of their Debts, And to ſupply what they could not otherwiſe for the preſent advance they took up Money upon Security of the Equity of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their whole Eſtate. Whereby, It plainly appears they uſed all wayes and meanes they were Capable of to raiſe Money, reſerving nothing but the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hope of their ground rent, which they are in Juſtice bound to preſerve as a Seed for their Poſterity, they having already paid, of their own Benevolence, and what they have ſo borrowed on Security of the remaining part of their Eſtate (which they have taken up for 7 years at 4 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi>) far above the real value (to be ſold) of what they receive thereout, over and above the yearly Charities, wherewith the ſame are Charged by the Donors: However (clouded with theſe Circumſtances) the work went but ſlowly on; the Generality of the Members that ſhould now have contributed their Aſſiſtance to diſcharge the whole being unſatisfied, as looking on the Gifts of ſome particular Perſons, to ſignifie little towards ſo great a work, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome better encouragement might be given to procure a ſubſcription of the whole Body of the Members; being of opinion, That ſo long as the Hall lay thus Ruinous, it wholly diſcouraged all. And under theſe ſad Circumſtances the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany continued, until it pleaſed God to move Sir <hi>John Moore,</hi> a Worthy Member of this Society, who taking into his conſideration its deplorable Condition every year leſſening in Reputation by reaſon of the Hall thus in Ruines, which not only diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged men to take their Freedoms, and Apprentices to be bound there; And Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors both in their life-time and by their Wills from their Liberality; But alſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the Society almoſt Contemptible: Out of his kindneſs and good Will towards this his own Company, was very inclineable at his own Charge to repair the Great Hall; hoping thereby to Encourage other Members by his Example to Contribute their Aſſiſtance either in re-Edifying or Augmenting the reſidue of their antient Seat. As the only means left to promote an Univerſal compliance of all the other Members, according to their ſeveral Degrees, and Abilities in liberal Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards diſcharge of the great Arrears of their Debts and Charities, which being made known to a Court of Aſſiſtants, Sir <hi>James Edwards,</hi> Maſter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany then preſent, was pleaſed in the name of the whole Court to declare unto Sir <hi>John Moore,</hi> then alſo preſent, That the firſt mention of ſuch his good intention towards them, had ſo grateful a Reſentment, that it had a kind influence upon all preſent; And therefore made it the Requeſt of the Court to him, on behalf of the Company, to purſue the ſame; Acquainting him, That he doubted not but it ſhould
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42278:7"/>be followed with ſo happy ſucceſs, that the <hi>Grocers Hall,</hi> which may juſtly Claim precedency of all Halls and publick Places within this City of <hi>London,</hi> for Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, and many other Conveniencies might in a ſhort time be made the moſt Commodious Habitation for a Lord Mayor. Whereupon Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> was pleaſed to declare, he would give five hundred pounds to repaire and beautifie the great Hall, That he might thereby incite other Members to follow in ſo good a Work; Provided, Care might be taken ſo to ſettle the ſame, That what ſhould be thus laid down might be ſo ſecured as to anſwer the good ends thereby deſign'd. Upon which ſo Worthy a Declaration, Mr. <hi>Beale</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bourne,</hi> two of the Wardens then preſent, by Agreement of the whole Court, undertook and promiſed forthwith to ſet about the work; And with all faithfulneſs to take Care the ſame ſhould be laid out to the beſt advantage accordingly, ſo as to have it finiſhed that Summer. And in order to Carry on ſo good a work (encouraged therein by ſeveral other Worthy Members then preſent) It was referred to the Wardens, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome other Members, calling to their Aſſiſtance ſuch Workmen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as they ſhould think fit, to Conſider off, and propound a Model of ſuch additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Building, in ſuch place as might make the Hall every way Commodious for Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Chief Magiſtrate of this City, both for Ornament and Uſe; And alſo by advice of Council, to ſettle the Hall and all the reſt of the Companies Revenue, (ſubject to the ſaid former ſecurities) ſo as it might anſwer theſe good ends, and ſecure (to the extent of it) the many yearly Charities payable by the Company, where there is no fund now left. Upon Report of which Committee, ſoon after Sir <hi>John Frederick,</hi> Sir <hi>James Edwards,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Tulſe,</hi> and ſeveral other Aldermen and Worthy Members a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to Contribute liberally towards the ſame Additional Building; For which a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble was ordered, and accordingly drawn and engroſſed whereby thoſe that were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers, declaring how ſenſible they were that if the Hall ſhould long Continue under theſe Circumſtances, Not only all that had been done would be wholly fruitleſs, but all that Remain, (for which they were Truſtees to the Generations to come) would ſoon waſte into nothing, which would reproachfully render the preſent Members moſt ungrateful to their Anceſtors, whoſe Names ſtill Bloſſom in what remains of thoſe Pious Monuments of their Charities, and obnoxious to thoſe who ſhould ſucceed happy Members of this Society.</p>
               <p>And therefore concluded the reparation of the Hall to be the only leading means left to preſerve the Society. And that, as Sir <hi>John Cutler</hi> had ſo long ſince for thoſe very ends, at his own Charges erected that ſtately Fabrick which is the Parlour and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Room over it in the Garden; And Sir <hi>John Moore</hi> had now undertaken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair and Beautify the great Hall: So they held themſelves highly obliged to promote and carry on ſo excellent a work. And having cauſed the Scite and Fabrick of the Hall to be ſurveyed, and finding, that with ſome more additional Building (then already propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be erected,) it might be made a more commodious and convenient Habitation for the Cheif Magiſtrate of this City, than any other within the City of <hi>London.</hi> Therefore encouraged by ſo good Examples, that it might anſwer all the good ends pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and might with all poſſible ſpeed be carried on and finiſhed, in order to invite and encourage a general Subſcription of all the Members towards payment of the Companies Debts and Charities, they Liberally Subſcribed and promiſed to pay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the raiſing and finiſhing of ſuch additional Building, the ſeveral Sums of Money there under, at their ſeveral names ſet down, and appearing, and declaring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (if occaſion ſhould be afterwards) to be further liberally aſſiſting to Compleat ſo good a work; Not doubting but their Brethren, the reſt of the Members, would every one follow according to their Degrees and Qualities. And that the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and repairing their Hall might not prove a Bait to ſuch Creditors (if any ſhould be) as formerly ſeized the Ruines of the ſame to endeavour again a Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt it; But might anſwer thoſe good ends ſo by them deſigned, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany for Encouragment of their Members in their Liberal Subſcriptions towards this great Work by advice of learned Council Conveyed the ſame, and all their Revenue, and the Equity of Redemption thereof (ſubject to the ſaid former Securities) to Truſtees to ſecure (as far as the ſame will extend) the yearly payment of thoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities for which they are Chargeable to ſeveral Pariſhes, Priſons, and Uſes by their Benefactors, who heretofore paid into their hands ſeveral great Sums of Money for thoſe Uſes (for which now no fund remains) that they might alſo thereby not only diſcharge their Conſciences towards God, and the Memory of ſuch Pious Benefactors, But alſo avoid the Chargeable Proſecutions of the Commiſſioners upon the Statute for Charitable Uſes who have of late put this Company every year to exceeding great Charges and Expences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42278:7"/>Thus have I endeavoured, to lay down the true State of the Company of <hi>Grocers,</hi> as it relates to themſelves, and their Creditors in their preſent Condition. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof, having been lately declared before my Lord Chancellor, by way of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a Creditors Bill (who is the only Perſon that now proſecutes any ſuit againſt them) ſeemed to give great ſatisfaction unto many Council; and other Perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned, who before, were ignorant of the true State of the Companies Condition. And may (happily) be a means to divert others, from proſecuting any ſuch Chargeable ſuit againſt the Company, in the event whereof, they cannot promiſe themſelves ſo much benefit, as they may now hope to receive without it. And ſince that, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and the reſt of the Commiſſioners for Charitable Uſes, having been likewiſe informed of the Companies Condition, and what they had ſo deſigned, and were in Proſecution of to preſerve their Reputation (beyond what they could either by Law, or Equity, be compelled to) were ſo well ſatisfied therein, that they adviſed the Proſecutors for the Charities, rather to apply themſelves to the Wardens, in a kind, and friendly Manner, and encourage the Members to go on in ſo good a work, than in vain (waſting the Pariſh Stock) again to diſturb them with Suites, to diſcourage the Members; and thereby, not only to hazard the loſs of their own, but to wrong all others concerned with them. And alſo ſeveral of their Creditors, who before were inſtigated by ſome unadviſed Perſons, to give the Company diſturbance, as ſoon as they were informed of their Caſe, better conſidered their own Intereſt, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbore; which not only afforded great Freedom, and Liberty to the Members in the Court of Aſſiſtants, to follow this undertaking, but alſo gave Wonderful Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the late Maſter, and Wardens, to begin; And to Sir <hi>Henry Tulſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Box,</hi> Mr. <hi>Winch</hi> and Mr. <hi>Reeve,</hi> the ſucceeding Maſter, and Wardens, for this preſent year, (to whom Mr. <hi>Beal,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bourn,</hi> (two of the late Wardens) at the requeſt of the Court of Aſſiſtants, willingly joyned themſelves to facilitate the work) to go on, who have (all as one man) been very Zealous, and Active, in this great work, of finiſhing the Hall in ſo ſhort a time, as is almoſt incredible; Eſpecially conſidering, that the ſame was many wayes (upon further Conſideration had) enlarged, and made more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, than at firſt was intended, with many Accommodations (not at firſt thought of) to render it ſo exactly (as indeed it is) far excelling any Hall that now is, or (proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) ever was in <hi>London,</hi> ſo that the whole Charge of compleating the ſame (I believe with as good husbandry as was poſſibly to be managed) yet ſwells to double the Sum, which was at firſt propounded to be disburſed, and therefore call'd for further Aſſiſtance, of more Members, than at firſt was deſigned, to Contribute to the ſame.</p>
               <p>And now the Hall being Compleatly finiſhed, as the only means propounded for Encouragement of all the Members, A Court of Aſſiſtants was call'd, in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and adviſe of the moſt ſpeedy, and effectual way, and method, to promote, and gain their Subſcriptions. And being met, the Court very ſeriouſly took into their Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the State of the Company, under their Circumſtances and their preſent Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities for Money, to carry on this great Work, of paying the Debts, and raiſing and reſtoring, the declining Reputation of the Company, deſigned by the new Building and Repairing the Hall, which, though the Charge amounts to a far greater Sum, than was at firſt propounded, to make it more Commodious, yet it manifeſtly appeared to have been the only means left; and, that without it, all others, would have been inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, to keep the Company of <hi>Grocers</hi> upon a Foundation, which, otherwiſe, muſt in a ſhort time have naturally diſſolved of it ſelf. For that the Apprentices, and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of any Eſtate, or Value, who before wholly declined, have now daily encreaſed, as having a proſpect, by what is viſible, of a proſperous carrying on the whole work, anſwerable thereto; And that, though this Charge of the Building, amounted to a great Sum, yet when they conſidered that the Company may probably receive yearly (if they pleaſe) as much as the intereſt of the Moneys therein disburſed amounts to; And that ſo great a part thereof, as was already paid would not have been given, upon any other Accompt; And that the work now compleated, is in it ſelf of far greater value than all the other part of the Companies Revenue (over and above the Charities iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereout) And that thoſe ſeveral ſums, ſo ſubſcribed, were thus freely given by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Worthy Members, on purpoſe for this great Work, that it might encourage the whole Members, freely, and liberally, to Contribute towards the reſidue of this Work, and the Debts. And that it is hoped, the whole harge will be ſo advanc'd, by kind Members, incited by the ſame motives; They unanimouſly reſolved, not only liberally to follow themſelves, but from thoſe great Examples, to recommend the carrying on the whole work, to a ſelect Committee, conſiſting of ſuch Members in every of the four Diviſions, then already made, whoſe opportunity, and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, they had great hopes, would engage them to improve their intereſt with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42278:8"/>their Brethren by the beſt Arguments they could uſe to ſtir them up to a liberal Contribution towards ſo acceptable a Work. The Court appointing the Wardens for the time being, and all ſuch kind Members as would be aſſiſting herein, or any two, or more of them (on whom the Clerk is from time to time ordered to attend with the Papers appointed for the Subſcription in every diviſion) to be a Committee for this work, who are by the Court, on behalf of the Company, deſired upon all occaſions, and with what ſpeed they could, or might poſſible, to ſhew themſelves good examples. And from thence preſs and ſtir up all other their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to Contribute towards diſcharging of the remainder of the ſaid Building, and the Companies Debts, That ſo great and good a Work, wherein ſo many thouſands are and may be concerned, might be chearfully carried on; and ſo might all (as Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-helpers) have the honour to be Recorded amongſt the Generations to come, The happy Repairers and Reſtorers of the Company of <hi>Grocers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far, by the good Providence of God proviſion is made, and encouragement given to all kind Members to joyn in Carrying on this great Work. And as thoſe at the Helm have endeavoured every way to promote the advantage of the Company, ſo their deſires are to leſſen the Burthen of their Brethren. In order whereto, they have reſtrained the renewing of any Leaſe of the Companies Eſtate; And by Order upon Order, barred acceſs to treat touching the ſame, whilſt there is 21 years in being. And alſo have ſunk the Charge of coming upon the Cloathing, and other Charge gradually aſcending to that degree; That they may undergo their Duty in this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, every way in their Turns, with more Eaſe and Chearfulneſs. And ſuch endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are uſing for the good of this Company, as I doubt not but in time will give greater Satisfaction, and Encouragement to the Members, than poſſibly they might have expected.</p>
               <p>And to avoid one great Evil frequently practized, by the Members of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, in Voluntarily, or deſignedly ſuffering their Apprentices to be bound at other Halls, to Members of other Companies, and ſo turned over to ſerve their times to them; (than which nothing can be more deſtructive to this Society) the Court of Aſſiſtants taking the ſame into their Conſideration, have by adviſe of learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil purſuant to their power given them by their Charter, and the Statute in that Caſe provided, made a By-law to reſtrain the ſame for the time to come enjoyning every Member of this Society (ſo far as may fairly lye in their own power) to forbear it for the future. And though (through miſapprehenſion, and for want of knowledge of the true ſtate of the Companies Condition) they have already done it, Yet when they have ſo much encouragement, to joyn their Aſſiſtance in this good Work begun; And ſhall conſider their Oathes both as Apprentices and Freemen (which is Motive enough to every Sincere, and juſt man, to purſue the ſame, unleſs ſuch as ſeek curious Evaſions to elude ſo ſacred a Tye) It is not to be doubted, but they will not only obſerve this, and all other Lawful Ordinances made for the good of the Fellowſhip according to their Oathes: But will in and by all other wayes, and means, to (their Power) promote the Intereſt, and advantage of this Company, as good Citizens, and Brethren.</p>
               <p>HAving thus Stated the Condition of the Company, as it long flouriſhed in Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and gradually through Various Providences, and the ſad effects of War, and Fire, how it groaned under ſo great preſſure in her ſadder Circumſtances; And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet before you the happy Encouragement already now given, and the Methods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded again to raiſe, and reſtore this Company to its former Splendor; I now turn to the Honourable, and Worthy Members, of whom it Conſiſts; And you my Noble, and good Maſters, under whom I hold my Station in this place, Bear, I humbly pray you, with my Zeal, and Freedom, and the boldneſs I aſſume, to move you, to ſet to your helping hands in this work, ſo excellent, and acceptable to God, and every Good Man:</p>
               <p n="1">I. By remembring you of thoſe Eminent Charities, For which thoſe Worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who went before you in former times, and are to this day Celebrated; And have left us ſuch grounds (as being now built) gives us the proſpect of a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue when the Leaſes are out, which though far diſtant, are and will be every year (like uſeful Timber,) a more growing hope to Poſterity.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:42278:8"/>II. That you would not only think it enough to praiſe them, but be provoked by a generous Emulation, to follow their Example, liberally and bountifully to afford your Aſſiſtance, Not only to ſecure but alſo to encreaſe this growing hope, that our Burthen and reproach, being removed, Our Benefactors may be encouraged, and this Society ſtill preſerved a Seminary of good Merchants, and a Treaſury of Charity; That ſo the ſucceeding Generations may bleſs and honour you, as much as you do thoſe Worthy Members in former times, when your Names ſhall be Recorded as Raiſers, and Reſtorers of the Company of <hi>Grocers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. That what you do you would do ſpeedily, whereby you will draw on others, that need quickening and encouragement by your Example; And in ſo doing, you will not only have the Comfort of what you do your ſelves, but be the happy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters in others, of what the Company will have Cauſe to bleſs God, and give you thanks for it.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That you will Conſider how great a Deliverance you had to eſcape the late Dreadful Fire with your Lives; And how Gracious God hath been to you, ſtill to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt you with his Talents lent for Improvement, as Stewards in his work. And that this Company which ſuffered ſo much in that Calamity, hath no other hands but yours, to repair her breaches.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That you can have no ſuch true Comfort in the World as to be Conſcious of doing of good Works of this Nature, when as faithful Stewards of that which is not Conſigned to you into property, but into truſt, you have (as good and faithful Servants,) but well diſpoſed of a parcel of your great Lord's Eſtate, according to his own Will.</p>
               <p>For though good works in themſelves (as flowing back from the Fountain from whence they ſpring) can be no way meritorious, Yet they have been alwayes, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, that we find in every Age, Eſtates continue longeſt in the Name, and Family, of ſuch as have been moſt diffuſive, in Works of this Nature; That if it were modeſt, to render a reaſon, why ſo many great Eſtates, are ſooner waſted by a looſe Heir, than gotten by his frugal Parent, it may well be preſumed, becauſe ſo little of it was beſtowed to ſuch Uſes: When men return ſo little to God, to whom they owe all they have. And moſt aſſuredly, no Article in your Accompt, at the great Audit, will ſooner be allowed, to Cover many other Errors, then what is thus diſpoſed; And now, as Spice is a great ingredient in this Myſtery, and is a part of your Arms; ſo I pray conſider, how Almes in Scripture are called, an Odor of a ſweet ſmelling Savour. And it is theſe perfumes, that will prove acceptible to God, and have a good Savour amongſt men. So I Conclude, with my Prayers to Almighty God, to encline all your hearts, according to your ſeveral Degrees and Qualities, in this great work, to acquit your ſelves, as good Citizens, and <hi>Grocers;</hi> And that I may be happy, in diſcharge of my Duty, which alone moved me to make this Addreſs to you. And ſhall be my Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to perform, As,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Right Honourable, Right Worſhipful, And the reſt of the Worthy Members, Your moſt faithful and moſt humble Servant,</hi> W. Ravenhill, <hi>Clerk of the Society of the Mystery of the</hi> Grocers.</signed>
               <dateline>Grocers-Hall, <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 12, 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
